Finding Aid for the Allegra Fuller Snyder papers, 1960-2010 LSC.1881
UCLA Library Special Collections
Allegra Fuller Snyder papers
1960-2010
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.1881
54 Linear Feet (107 boxes)
Research, personal and professional files of Allegra Fuller Snyder, professor emeritus and past chair of UCLA Dance Department and World Arts and Cultures. Her research areas included performance dance, dance ethnology, dance therapy, and film as a method of preserving and documenting dance.
107 boxes (54 linear ft.)
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Allegra Fuller Snyder, 2011.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9969303203606533
Biography
Allegra Fuller Snyder, an early Chair of UCLA's Dance Department (1974-1980, Spring 1984, and 1990-1991), founding Coordinator / Chair for the Ethnic Arts Program cum World Arts and Cultures Department (1972-1983), Chair of the Faculty of the School of Arts (1989-1991), and Professor of Dance/Dance Ethnology retired from UCLA in 1991. She was long-active with the Congress on Research in Dance (CORD) and the National Endowment of Arts, dance division.
Snyder's areas of interest include: performance dance, dance ethnology, dance therapy, and film as a method of preserving/documenting dance. An early advocate of dance preservation on film for use in education, she produced historical films about Mary Wigman and about Baroque dance, a performance dance film about Margalit Oved Marshall. Her husband, film documentarian Robert Snyder, cooperated with her in the making of an ethnographic film about the Philippine dance troupe Bayanihan. She was a key consultant on "Dancing" for Thirteen WNET.
Snyder attended the School of American Ballet (1941-1947), received her BA in dance from Bennington College (1951), and earned her MA in dance from UCLA (1967). The only living child of R. Buckminster Fuller, she was born Aug. 18, 1927 in Chicago, IL. She was the founder and first president of the Buckminster Fuller Institute, presently located in Brooklyn NY.
Scope and Content
This collection includes the research, personal and professional files of Allegra Fuller Snyder, professor emeritus and past chair of the UCLA Dance Department and the World Arts and Cultures Department. It is evident in her files that AFS's professional and personal endeavors are often indistinct.
The collection is arranged in four series: personal organizational files, UCLA administrative papers, performance programs, and research materials and organizations files.
The personal organizational files are Snyder's files as she maintained them for her own use. They include obituaries, and articles about and correspondence with friends and colleagues. The transcript for an oral history interview of Snyder is located here.
UCLA administrative papers include Snyder's academic papers, university newsletters, and UCLA committee and faculty papers. The early years of the Dance Department and development of the Ethnic Arts Program cum World Arts and Cultures (WAC) department are addressed, here.
Performance programs is a collection of several decades of published ephemera of performances that Snyder attended.
Research materials and organizations files include information and correspondence about students, colleagues, research, and her father, R. Buckminster Fuller. As a member of a large number of organizations, Snyder's products from her research (presentations, lectures, articles, descriptions of films, photos, audio tapes) are included. There are substantial files that address the years that Snyder was active with the Congress on Research in Dance and serving as a panelist for the dance division of the National Endowment for the Arts and for the Humanities. Her research with the Yaqui Indians and dance preservation and education through film are represented.
Snyder maintained her files alphabetically and by date, for the most part. There were many instances of overlapping and incongruous filing styles (ex. recent to old, old to recent) that may have been due to changing office assistants. Sometimes the items were just placed in a new folder while another existed for it, starting a new series. Discrete groupings of files were formed as they were moved into storage.
Initialisms and Acronyms used in Snyder's Research
AADC - Association of American Dance Companies
AADE - Australian Association for Dance Education
AAHPER - American Association for Health, Physical Education, and Recreation
AAUW - American Association of University Women
ADF - American Dance Festival
ADG - American Dance Guild (see NDG)
ADTA - American Dance Therapy Association
AFS - Allegra Fuller Snyder
AISC - American Indian Studies Center
APASI - Asian Performing Arts Summer Institute
APPEX - Asian Pacific Performance Exchange Program
ARS - Artists Rights Society
ASA - African Studies Association
AWARE - Association for Women's Active Return to Education
CAFAM - Craft and Folk Art Museum
CCA - California Confederation of the Arts
CCDC - City Contemporary Dance Company
CCDR - Cross Cultural Dance Resources
CDEA - California Dance Educators Association
CDF - Colorado Dance Festival
CID - Conseil International de la Danse (see also IDC)
CMER - Center for Movement Education and Research
CODA - Council of Dance Administrators
CORD - Congress on Research in Dance (earlier known as Committee on Research in Dance)
CSSSA - California State Summer School for the Arts
CTA - California Teachers Association
CUCC - Committee on Undergraduate Courses and Curricula
DCA - Dance Critics Association
DDBP - Dance Database Project
DEF - Dance Ethnology Forum
DESIN - Dance Ethnology Service Information Network
DFA - Dance Films Association, Inc.
DHC - Dance Heritage Coalition
DNB - Dance Notation Bureau
DRC - Dance Resource Center
DSLA - Dance South LA Project
EFLA - Educational Film Library Association, Inc.
IAC - Institute of American Cultures
ICTM - International Council for Traditional Music
IDA - International Documentary Association
IDC - International Dance Council (see also CID)
IDII - Isadora Duncan International Institute
IFMC - International Folk Music Council
ISOMATA - Idyllwild School of Music and the Arts
ISOP - International Studies and Overseas Programs UCLA
ITI - International Theatre Institute (Unesco)
JOHPER - Journal of Health, Physical Education, Recreation
LAADA - Los Angeles Area Dance Alliance
LACAE - Legislative Action Coalition for Arts Education
NARB - National Association for Regional Ballet
NARF - Native American Rights Fund
NASD - National Association of Schools of Dance
NCA - National Council on the Arts
NDG - National Dance Guild (see ADG)
NEA - National Endowment for the Arts
NEH - National Endowment for the Humanities
NIPAD - National Initiative to Preserve America's Dance
NRCD - National Resource Centre for Dance
PAF - Performing Arts Friendship Mission of Japan
PAW - Performing Arts Workshop
SASHM - Society for the Anthropological Study of Human Movement
SAVICOM - Society for the Anthropology of Visual Communication
SDHS - San Diego High School
SDSU - San Diego State University
SEM - Society for Ethnomusicology
SGSR - Society for General Systems Research
TAASP - The Association for the Anthropological Study of Play
WAC - World Arts and Cultures program at UCLA
WDA - World Dance Alliance
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Personal Organizational Files
UCLA Administrative Papers
Performance Programs
Research Materials and Organizations Files
Women dancers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Snyder, Allegra Fuller --Archives.
- Personal Organizational Files, 1960-2010
  Scope and Contents note
  These two sets of alphabetical folders have been inter-filed, though the folder contents are as AFS used them. One set makes up her active files (at the time of acquisition 2011), and the second set is from her inactive files. The files consist of articles and obituaries written about notable personalities in the worlds of dance and other arts, health, science, film, ethnography. The files include academic articles; publicity information about or by students and AFS colleagues; and letters of recommendation for job searches, grant proposals, and degree applications. Also includes formal and personal correspondence about AFS's research, about Buckminster Fuller, and from friends and family. The transcript for an oral history interview of AFS is found in this series.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES INCLUDES DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Abbot, Sally., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence from AFS's cousin.
  - Adler, Janet., 1995-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence. "Authentic Movement Institute" spring 2001.
  - Advocates for the Arts., 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Proposal for UCLA School of Law to provide free legal support of art groups and individuals. "Innovative Teaching in the Area of Fine Arts and the Law."
  - Aguado, Oscar., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "The Form" by Aguado and David Zucker. Photocopied letter from Buckminster Fuller.
  - Ailian, Dai., 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Obituary of founder of Beijing Dance Academy, China.
  - Alexandra, Madame., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "Modern Maturity" article about ballet teacher Alexandra Baldina Kosloff, formerly prima ballerina from Bolshoi of St. Petersburg, Russia.
  - Alpert Awards (1 of 2)., 1999-2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Herb Alpert Foundation and the California Institute of the Arts awards programs. Ralph Lemon 1999 application. AFS presented award to Lemon.
  - Alpert Awards (2 of 2)., 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Herb Alpert Foundation and the California Institute of the Arts awards programs, application packets.
  - Alum Dance Foundation., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Correspondence from Manuel Alum.
  - Alvin Ailey American Dance Theatre., 1998-2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Articles including Judith Jamison's Nov. 29, 1998 New York Times article "DANCE; Missing Alvin Ailey as a New Era Dawns."
  - Alwin Nikolais Dance Theater., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Photocopy of book review.
  - Amberson Associates., 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Correspondence with Rosanne Amberson regarding ethnic dance filmmaking.
  - American Association for Heath, Physical Education, and Recreation (AAHPER)., 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Correspondence from Araminta Little. 88th Anniversary Convention - Dance Division, Minnesota. AAHPER Update Oct., 1973.
  - American Dance Festival (ADF)., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    50th Anniversary Dance Festival presenter / attendee packet. First International Modern Dance Festival.
  - American Dance Guild (ADG)., 1974-2005 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Correspondence. ADG Newsletter summer 1994, autumn 1995, summer 1996, winter 1996, fall / winter 1998-99, Vol 48 No 1 2005.
  - American Dance Guild (ADG) Committee on awards 1973., 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Correspondence. National Executive Board Meeting minutes 1972.
  - American Dance Therapy Association (ADTA)., 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Authentic Movement Institute brochure. American Dance Therapy Association 35th annual conference "The Geography of Belonging in the 21st Century: Psyche, culture & profession."
  - American Folklife Center., 1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    "American Folklife: A Commonwealth of Cultures."
  - Anderson, Alyne., 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Resume, correspondence.
  - Anderson, Erika Surat., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Postcard regarding "Turbans" film.
  - Apostolos-Cappadona, Diane., 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    AFS correspondence with Apostolos-Cappadona-religion and visual arts author, editor, and teacher.
  - Applewhite, Edmund Jarrat (EJ)., 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondence. The paper "Invisible Evolution in the Works of O.B. Hardison and His Contemporaries." 2005 obituary states that he collaborated with Buckminster Fuller.
  - Armstrong, Gayle., 1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    "International Folk Culture Center" newsletter Oct., 1992.
  - Arts Genesis-Tucson, AZ., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Aug. and Sept. 1990 newsletters. ArtsReach and Project Choki information about arts education for Indian children. See also Box 107, folder 1.
  - Asawa, Ruth., 1995-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Student of Buckminster Fuller at Black Mountain College. Museum and gallery exhibit postcards, brochures. Public school work outreach material. Husband William Albert Lanier's 2008 obituary.
  - Ashley, Wayne., 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Correspondence and CV.
  - Astaire, Fred., 1959-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Newsclippings and movie promo photos.
  - Atmadibrata, Enoch., 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with the Executive Director of the West Java Cultural Project, Indonesia. "Bulletin Kebudayaan Jawa Barat" 1, 2, and 3.
  - Attitudes & Arabesques., 1993, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Current listings of dance volumes at the Leslie Getz Dance Library in New York City.
  - Austin, Susan., 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Co-founder of the City of Angels Ice Theatre June 6 letter.
  - Australian Association for Dance Education (AADE)., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Executive Officer Julie Dyson Sept. 16 letter.
  - Avalos, Ava., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Letter of recommendation, CV, correspondence.
  - Awards-AFS., 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Arts Genesis Acknowledgement, 1995-96; Who's Who in American Education, 1992-93; James S. Coleman African Studies Center Certificate of Appreciation, 1991. Hezbon Edward Owiti block prints.
  - Babuscio, Elisabeth Whitfield Galloway., 1979, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Letter with "The 20th Century War Dance." San Diego Unified School District Evaluation.
  - Baker, Laurence Wilfred (Laurie)., 2007 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Obituary for the British cum Indian architect of low-cost houses.
  - Balanchine, George., 1989-2004 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Online and newspaper clippings. "Balanchine Celebration, New York City Ballet" May 4-June 27, 1993 program.
  - Bales, Bill., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Memorial correspondence and programming for the 1951-67 Chairperson of Bennington College's Dance Faculty.
  - Bandem, I Made., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Correspondence concerning the head of Bali's College of Indonesian Arts' presentation in Hawaii, "The Evolution Legong: From sacred to secular dance of Bali." Newsclippings. Ann Nishiguchi's paper "Style & Movement in Okinawan Classical Dance."
  - Barnes, Molly., undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    "How To Get Hung" promotional flyer for guide for emerging artists and art professionals.
  - Barragan, Pat., 1997 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Note and gift certificate for Feldenkrais Functional Integration. Informational packet for Center for Physical Health, Movement Forward.
  - Bartenieff, Irmgard., 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Correspondence. "Body/Space/Effort: Coping with the environment" 1977.
  - Baryshnikov, Mikhail., 1977-2003 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Newsclippings and magazine articles.
  - Barzel, Ann., 1996 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    New York Times article about the teacher and reviewer of dance.
  - Bates, Gary., 2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Dance Resource Center Dancezine featuring the Los Angeles Legend, Sept./Oct.
  - Bateson, Gregory., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Cultural anthropologist and UC Regent's obituary.
  - Bausch, Pina., 1996 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    UCLA Today article on the Tanztheater Wuppertal dance company, Feb. 12.
  - Baykal-Rollins, Jeffrey., 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Correspondence to the Buckminster Fuller Institute with exhibition proposal and diagram.
  - Beach, Albert., 2004 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Gallery exhibit brochure.
  - Bear Island., 2005 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Correspondence, budgets concerning the family shareholdings of communal property.
  - Bear Island Centennial Book., 2010 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, agendas and book draft of family communal property.
  - Beckett, Samuel., 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Article entitled, "Samuel Beckett: The exaltation of absurdity."
  - Beiswanger, George., 1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Obituary.
  - Belilove, Lori., 2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Isadora Duncan Dance Foundation letter and promotional flyer, postcard.
  - Bella Lewitzky Dance Co.., 1975-2004 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Dance Associates Foundation Newsletter 3. Correspondence. Dance Gallery press release. Newsclippings, photocopies of articles. Modern Dance "Los Angeles Choreographer: Bella Lewitsky" article. Keynote speech for 1989 CDEA. Obituary. Memorial program and Regent's Lecture. List of awards received.
  - Bennington (1 of 4)., 1964-2004 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Official and unofficial correspondence, Spring/ Summer 2004 "Alumni Magazine," articles about college and alums, "Bennington Revisited, A Study of 152 Women of the Classes of 1942 through 1946: Preliminary findings," May 1985 and winter 1988 "Quadrille," 1994 petition to protest mass firings, 1964 list of alumnae in Southern California, 1968 Dance Tour, Class of 1945 list.
  - Bennington (2 of 4)., 1963-2004 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Official and unofficial correspondence; Aug. 1964 "Bulletin;" May and Nov. 1963, Feb. and May 1964, Feb. 1965 "Bulletin-Alumnae Issue;" fall 1989 and fall 1990 "Dance Letter."
  - Bennington (3 of 4)., 1968-1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Spring 1993 "Dance Letter," "The Book on Bennington: 1992-1994," "Symposium Report of the Bennington College Board of Trustees," "Alumnae Directory 1968 -1970."
  - Bennington (4 of 4)., 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Official and unofficial correspondence, spring 2001 and spring 2002 "The Alumni Magazine," "The Arts and Society: Looking ahead" by Elizabeth Coleman Pres., "50th Reunion Class of 1951," Photo of Ben Belitt painting.
  - Bennington Dance Faculty Application., 1968-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Correspondence.
  - Bennington Honorary Co-Chair for Campaign., 1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Committee acceptance cards, correspondence, LA Area campaign committee list. April 7 "Statement From the Board of Trustees."
  - Biegel, Heidi., 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Correspondence, CV about post-partum care.
  - Bernhardt, Elise., 1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Brochure for "The Kitchen" in New York.
  - Billingsley, Joseph Horace., 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Letter to George W. Bush.
  - Bird, Bonnie., 1989-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Brochure and two letters. Informational packet "Transitions" from the Laban Centre for Movement and Dance.
  - Blacking, John., undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Photocopy of article "Dance, conceptual thought and production in the archaeological record."
  - Boas, Franziska., 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Boiles, Charles Lafayette (C.L.)., undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Photocopy of article "Danza."
  - Bondi, Don., 1990s-2000 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Dance Chair of the Los Angeles County High School for the Arts. Dance Dept. brochure, newsclipping of Stella Matsuda "Nisei," CDEA Heritage Award to Bondi and speech honoring him by Leslie Bisno.
  - Borger, Irene., 1995-2001 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Photocopy of article "From a Burning House" and "Witness" collection of short stories from the AIDS Project Los Angeles Writers Workshop Collection. Alpert Award correspondence. Article about her in "Quadrille." Correspondence. Cal Arts catalog. Jo Ann Callis brochure.
  - Borland, John Nelson., 1994 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Funeral flyer.
  - Boucher, Christine., 2001 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Yearly reflections letter.
  - Bracamonte, Laura., undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    "Inca, The Peruvian Music & Dance Ensemble" brochure.
  - Bradley, Karen Kohn., 1999 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    AFS letter of recommendation for Bradley.
  - Brentwood Dance Library., 1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    AFS book recommendations for building a dance library and letter from Glorya Kaufman thanking AFS for the book list. The Golden Thread Newsletter.
  - Brook, Peter., 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    New York Times Magazine Oct. 4 article "Peter Brook Creates a Nine- Hour Epic." Vogue Oct. article "Peter Brook Makes Believers of Us All."
  - Brown, Joie Vischer., 2004-2006 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Brown, Robert and Pogofsky-Harris, Elisse., 1998-2010 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Pogofsky-Harris Frye Art Museum catalog. Ojai Fall article "Here Come the Groom" about Brown.
  - Bruin Woods., 1990 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Correspondence about AFS being part of Guest Lecture Series.
  - Bruwer, Michael J.., 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Correspondence and newsclippings about Buckminster Fuller Institute.
  - Buckland, Theresa Jill., 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    AFS reference for Buckland's University of Surrey and Manchester Metropolitan University applications. CV. Correspondence.
  - Buffalo, State University College., 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Donald Kutschall correspondence about terminal degree status.
  - Buirge, Susan., 1990 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Photocopy of Le Monde article "La voyageuse."
  - Bulitt, Patricia (1 of 2)., 1993-2009 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Hooper Bay, Alaska Elder Eskimo "Their Eyes Have Seen the Old Dances." Promotional materials and correspondence.
  - Bulitt, Patricia (2 of 2)., 1990-2010 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    "Our Neighbors Dance Their Dances" brochure. Draft of "Alaskan Eskimo Dance." Promotional materials and correspondence. Hooper Bay, Alaska Elder Eskimo dance.
  - Bullock-Cormier, Barbara., 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Resume.
  - Burr, R. Page., 1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Byrd, Melinda., 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cage, John., 1992-2006 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Obituaries and Merce Cunningham personal note about memorial. AFS writing on 1948 Black Mountain connection and "It Was John's Laugh" written in his honor. "Geodesic Mathematics and Random Chaos John Cage and Buckminster Fuller" 2006 exhibition informational packet at Northern Illinois University.
  - Caldwell, Christine., 1995-2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Spring 2000 newsletter of the Moving Cycle Institute. "The Moving Center" informational material. Spring 1995 "ReVision" journal. Correspondence.
  - California Arts Council., 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Correspondence. "Organizational Support Program" 1991-1992 applications. "Guide to Programs: 1991-1992" and "1993 Guide to Programs."
  - California Institute of the Arts (1 of 2)., 1963-1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    1963-1965 catalog. Correspondence. Dec. 1970; Mar. 1971; Sept., Dec. 1973; and March, May, Sept. 1974 "CalArts the Bridge." Varied publications and newsclippings.
  - California Institute of the Arts (2 of 2)., 1970-1978 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Bulletin 1971-1972. Sept. 1971; June, Oct., Dec. 1972; Feb., April 1973 "CalArts the Bridge." Nov. 1975; Aug. / Sept., Nov. 1976; Jan., Feb., July / Aug. 1977 "CalArts Today." 1977-1978 catalog and "Report to Friends." Correspondence.
  - California Dance Educators Association (CDEA)., 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Members lists. Legislative Action Coalition for Arts Education (LACAE) informational flyers. Area Committee Chairmen lists.
  - California Dance Educators Association (CDEA) Conference., 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Correspondence about 1973 conference.
  - California Dance Educators Association (CDEA) Newsletters., 1973-2003 (Box 6, Folder 3)